<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Nick Knowlson</title>
 <link href="http://nickknowlson.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://nickknowlson.com/"/>
 <updated>2011-08-06T16:20:30-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://nickknowlson.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Nick Knowlson</name>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Hello World!</title>
   <link href="http://nickknowlson.com/blog/2011/07/23/hello-world/"/>
   <updated>2011-07-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://nickknowlson.com/blog/2011/07/23/hello-world</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This site is finally live! I have put a skeleton of content up here for now just so I can get it up, but over the coming months I&amp;#8217;ll be updating my Project pages with more detail as well as screenshots. I&amp;#8217;ll also put up the occasional blog post from time to time, and these will lean towards longer, more technical posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I meant the logo up above to be temporary, but it is kind of growing on me, so it may stay for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The css and javascript are a bit clunky at the moment as well, but they work well enough for the moment, and there will be lots of time to optimize the heck out of them in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s about all for the introductory post, the next one will probably be about something more interesting!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Command line file transfer</title>
   <link href="http://nickknowlson.com/blog/2009/02/05/command-line-file-transfer/"/>
   <updated>2009-02-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://nickknowlson.com/blog/2009/02/05/command-line-file-transfer</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;**Old post alert**&lt;/strong&gt; This is an old post I dug up from sometime around college)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve gotten really used to using bash now, so it&amp;#8217;s always a drag when I want to upload a file using sftp and lose my aliases, tab completion and everything else from my .bashrc. It&amp;#8217;s also more of a pain to copy directories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there are a couple of replacements for the default sftp client, and up until now, I had only tried lftp briefly. It was better,but not quite what I was looking for, and I found a bit awkward to use. Although that part could just be my own inexperience with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I just stumbled upon a solution to my problem that is dead simple and ALSO lets me get all the power and ease of use my personalized bash environment. Double win! It&amp;#8217;s called &lt;a href='http://fuse.sourceforge.net/sshfs.html'&gt;sshfs&lt;/a&gt; (SSH FileSystem), it&amp;#8217;s in the Debian and Ubuntu package repos already, and I doubtless should have found it a long time ago. It lets you mount a directory on your remote machine using ssh. Magical!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you need it, here&amp;#8217;s a quick runthrough of what you need to get this working:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='bash'&gt;sudo aptitude install sshfs
sshfs user@host: localmountpoint
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It defaults to your home directory as the point to mount, but if you want to you can specify a location after &amp;#8216;host:&amp;#8217; like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='bash'&gt;sshfs user@host:/home/user/data/ localmountpoint
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;#8217;re done, you can unmount it with this command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='bash'&gt;fusermount -u localmountpoint
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it a location that you use frequently like me, you could put an alias in your .bash_aliases file so mounting is a single &amp;#8216;mount_server&amp;#8217; command, and unmounting is &amp;#8216;unmount_server&amp;#8217;. Now when I want to upload something it&amp;#8217;s as painless as using cp or mv!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Haskell for great good</title>
   <link href="http://nickknowlson.com/blog/2009/01/14/haskell-for-great-good/"/>
   <updated>2009-01-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://nickknowlson.com/blog/2009/01/14/haskell-for-great-good</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;**Old post alert**&lt;/strong&gt; This is an old post I dug up from sometime around college)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;#8217;ve been doing bits of the &lt;a href='http://learnyouahaskell.com/'&gt;Learn You A Haskell For Great Good&lt;/a&gt; tutorial every now and then, and I just came across this &lt;a href='http://intoverflow.wordpress.com/2009/01/13/why-haskell-is-beyond-ready-for-prime-time/'&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; on Integer Overflow about why Haskell is &amp;#8220;ready for Prime Time&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I&amp;#8217;ve learned a bit about the basics, being told that I am able to search a repository of libraries by &lt;em&gt;type signature&lt;/em&gt; is really exciting. His example really drives it home even for those who don&amp;#8217;t know any Haskell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the other things I&amp;#8217;ve read about Haskell in other articles (mostly that it will introduce you to new paradigms and &lt;em&gt;blow your mind&lt;/em&gt;) I am now more firmly committed than ever to do some kind of project in Haskell, just to see what it feels like.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Vim as an IDE</title>
   <link href="http://nickknowlson.com/blog/2008/12/16/vim-as-an-ide/"/>
   <updated>2008-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://nickknowlson.com/blog/2008/12/16/vim-as-an-ide</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;**Old post alert**&lt;/strong&gt; This is an old post I dug up from sometime around college)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://i.imgur.com/8Yopn.png'&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href='http://i.imgur.com/pZtNP.png'&gt;screenshots&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my linux class last year, I was introduced to vim, and I&amp;#8217;ve been fairly impressed with its powerful text-editing capabilities. What I didn&amp;#8217;t know is that it really can just about replace an IDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What features does an IDE have that make it more useful than most text editors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being able to jump to the definition of a variable, function, class etc.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Autocompletion of variables, functions, classes etc.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Outline of a class, with variables and functions&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Project explorer&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Syntax highlighting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compile-time error checking&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Step by step debugger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refactoring across projects&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Automatic insertion of language specific code (ex: imports needed in Eclipse, generate getters and setters in java, files that Visual Studio makes when you use the visual editor, templates in Dreamweaver)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that&amp;#8217;s quite a bit. Vim can do the first group perfectly, can sort of do the second group ( depending on language), and can&amp;#8217;t do the last one. At least as far as I know, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just recently I&amp;#8217;ve been interested in editing php with vim, so here&amp;#8217;s a few things I found out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/164-Vim-Productivity-Tips-for-PHP-Developers.html'&gt;PHP parser check and running current file with the CLI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add the following to your .vimrc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;quot; run file with PHP CLI (F5)
autocmd FileType php noremap &amp;lt;F5&amp;gt; :w!&amp;lt;CR&amp;gt; :!$HOME/bin/php %&amp;lt;CR&amp;gt;

&amp;quot; PHP parser check (F4)
autocmd FileType php noremap &amp;lt;F4&amp;gt; :!usr/bin/php -l &amp;lt;CR&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I changed the mappings to the function keys because &amp;#60;c-m&amp;#62; corresponds to &amp;#60;return&amp;#62; as well, which I find annoying because I like to use CTRL+ movement keys for changing windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.vim.org/scripts/script.php?script_id=69'&gt;Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like what it sounds like, it opens a side window that keeps track of all your folders and files in the project that you specify. Has lots of neat features, including a project-wide search and replace, which can be useful. I suggest adding this to your .vimrc to have a &amp;#8216;Project toggle&amp;#8217; rather than typing :Project each time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;nmap &amp;lt;silent&amp;gt; &amp;lt;F10&amp;gt; &amp;lt;plug&amp;gt;ToggleProject&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, since by default folds have a hideous color scheme in my theme, I added this to my .vimrc to change that a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hi Folded ctermbg=0 ctermfg=3
hi FoldColumn ctermbg=0 ctermfg=3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;#8217;ve got the Project plugin installed, \C while in the Project window is the command that you&amp;#8217;ll probably want to use to help set up your first project (this took me a while). Also, make sure to use the help file that comes with the script (:help project).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.vim.org/scripts/script.php?script_id=273'&gt;Taglist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This opens up a side window that shows a list of classes, variables and functions in all files that you have open at the time. I set a a taglist toggle in my .vimrc file with this line: nmap &amp;#60;silent&amp;#62; &amp;#60;f12&amp;#62; :TlistToggle&amp;#60;cr&amp;#62;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In taglist.vim I changed a couple of the values so that it would look a bit better:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;let Tlist_Use_Right_Window = 1 &amp;quot;so that it doesn&amp;#39;t conflict with the project plugin
let Tlist_WinWidth = 25 &amp;quot;make it a bit slimmer
let Tlist_Enable_Fold_Column = 0 &amp;quot;Disable the fold column (it&amp;#39;s thick and not too useful for me)
let Tlist_Inc_Winwidth = 0 &amp;quot;Don&amp;#39;t attempt to resize my terminal - this may vary depending on how you are running vim&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/134-exuberant-ctags-with-PHP-in-Vim.html'&gt;Using ctags well&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lets you jump around to the definition of functions, classes etc. Just follow his instructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Autocompletion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#60;c-x&amp;#62; + &amp;#60;c-?&amp;#62; when in insert mode. You get a list of letters that can be used in place of ? when you press . Some notable ones are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;c-f&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; File - Autocompletes file names&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;c-n&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;c-p&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; Forward, Back respectively&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;c-i&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; Path - keywords in the current and included files&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;c-o&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; Omni - Omni complete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks and full credit to Matthew Weier O&amp;#8217;Phinney, whose &lt;a href='http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/164-Vim-Productivity-Tips-for-PHP-Developers.html'&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; started me on all of this and indeed is the source of many of these tips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#8217;t cover debugging, I&amp;#8217;ll save it for a later post maybe. If you&amp;#8217;re interested, go ahead and &lt;a href='http://www.vim.org/scripts/script_search_results.php?keywords=debug&amp;amp;amp;script_type=&amp;amp;amp;order_by=downloads&amp;amp;amp;direction=descending&amp;amp;amp;search=search'&gt;search the scripts&lt;/a&gt; for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, here&amp;#8217;s some &lt;a href='http://stackoverflow.com/questions/95072/what-are-your-favorite-vim-tricks'&gt;vim tips and tricks&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
